Hello.  Welcome back
to Lam Rim.
Today we're going to do a review
of the entire course.  It's
good for me.
I'd like to do a review myself.
This format of producing the episodes
separately
and then doing them at different times
seems to lose the flow of the entire
teaching.
I thought it would be nice if today we went back to
the beginning and flowed
through all the teachings of Lam Rim
that we have had.
I'm going to flow in that way based
on the idims,
the idea-images,
that we use to teach
ACI teachers.
ACI teachers are expected to be
able to look at one
of these images
and identify the idea behind it.
I think... Tim, how many did we say there would
be?  A thousand or something like that?
How many?
Something like 500.
So it's easy to take the test,
to examine someone based solely
on photos,
so we're only presenting you with
these photos.
So I challenge you during this review:
when we put up a picture, I'll
give you a second and see if you can remember
what the picture was about.  Alright
?  This is a good review
of the entire course we are doing.
Okay, here we go.
First image Mr. Sejii.
This image is supposed to
remind you
that we are halfway through the practices
for average-ability people,
and what they are trying to achieve is nirvana.  They are
trying to get off the Wheel
of Life,
out of all personal suffering.
This is where Buddha taught
the three trainings
that will help you reach
your personal nirvana.
The third training is understanding emptiness,
understanding the feather.
The second training is meditation.
At a deep level, these two
can only be done
in a quiet place, during certain
times of the day,
when you are really focusing
on your meditation mat.
At a deep level, these two should be done
during special times of the day,
but this one,
the basis of the other two, which is being kind
to people,
you can call it morality,
you could call it an ethical lifestyle,
but in the end it is being kind to people.
That is the foundation we always have
at our disposal all day long.
This is one of the three extraordinary trainings
of Buddhism,
in order to help us achieve nirvana.
And we have it available all day.
So, in this image
you can see Seiji helping Geshe Michael
to decrypt his computer.
Which is one of the nicest things young people
can do for older people.
Next image.
See if you can remember
what this image was.  Did
you guess?
This lady is paying her taxes.
What does this make it in the
Lam Rim system?  It
makes her...
a Dharma teacher.
When I say Dharma master,
or tantric master, I
already know the image you have in your mind:
it's a great lama on a throne
with a big yellow hat,
maybe they're ringing a bell
and a small drum and they're...
and you think, "'Oh, he's a Dharma master,
he's a real Dharma master.'"
Or you're thinking about that old picture
of Nagarjuna,
and it's all very mystical.
But in truth, in Lam Rim,
what we learned
was about this woman.
She has two children, is married,
and is a Dharma teacher.
She is a true Dharma master.
Pabongka Rinpoche said,
"Don't think that a Dharma master
has to be sitting on a throne
reciting some tantric ritual."
This lady is doing... what?  He
is paying his taxes.
Being honest with your taxes
is really difficult in my country.  It
can take weeks to prepare
your taxes,
to prepare them carefully,
to do them with complete honesty,
to pay every penny you're supposed to
pay.
This makes her...
She has the first of the
extraordinary trainings of a good person, to
be kind to people,
and that makes her a true
Dharma master.
Forget those images you have
of lamas with big hats,
and ringing bells.  That's easy,
anyone can do that.
Being kind to people is difficult,
and maintaining your morality, maintaining
your ethics, is also difficult.
The next one.  I'll
give you a moment.  Do you remember
what this is about?
The quote in the Lam Rim was:
(TSUL KHRIMS LDAN PA'I DGE SLONG
'OD DANG LDAN)
A person who is really keeping
his vows,
really keeping his Buddhist guidelines,
especially the ten rules,
shines, really shines.
A person who is making a healthy,
modest, and discreet effort to keep their commitments,
to maintain the ten good karmas, to
be kind to people,
has a calm look on their face,
is glowing.
When they enter a room, you know it,
everyone starts to feel better.
Like Tim and Seiji.
That is a light in the world.
Buddha said, "Those people are the light
of the world."
There is a Christian expression:
Don't put a candle in a basket.
Let the world see your happy face.
And that is a light,
a true guiding light for the whole
world.
Next image.  Idim number 4
Yes. This is a cliff I went to
with my partner Veronica
for her birthday, during this Lam Rim.  They
were talking about the sunset,
whose word in Tibetan is (NUB PA).  It is
also the word for west,
because the sun sets in the west.
So (NUB PA) means:
the sunset.
And this is a very sad verb.
This is a very sad idea in the Dharma.
The most famous place is at the end
of the Abhidharmakosha,
The Treasury House
of Higher Wisdom.
The Treasure House of Higher Knowledge,
of Master Vasubhandu,
and he says:
"The sun of Dharma, the light of Dharma,
will be hidden in this world."
We will lose the light of the Dharma
in this world.
This world will enter into darkness.
After a certain time,
the Buddha's teachings will disappear
from this world.
First they disappear from
people's minds,
but they will still be in libraries; those books
are still in libraries.
Probably in libraries that John Brady has
not yet found.
And later they will also disappear from libraries,
and then they will disappear completely.
I put the photo here because Pabongka Rinpoche
made a special observation,
saying,
"If you cannot keep your commitments,
if you cannot maintain
'good behavior with people,
' then we can say that the Dharma
has left this world.
The light of the Dharma has left this world
within you."  "
The sun has set inside
your own chest."
Which would be a very sad thing,
if we don't keep our vows.
Next picture.
Yes. We called this retreat Love
in the Time of the Virus.
The point was that during a
very difficult time in the world,
if you keep your commitments,
if you are kind to people
when things are scary,
frightening, the virus is spreading, we do
n't know where, we don't know how, we do
n't know how many people are going to
die...
If during those difficult times
you do something good for other people, it
is much, much more powerful.
He mentioned, if you remember, a 5-star Buddha paradise.
Which is like a perfect place,
it's easy to be a good person, everyone
there is a good person.
That's not a great achievement. It's not
the big deal, and the seed
isn't that powerful,
being kind in a group
of nice people.
Being kind when people are attacking you,
when people are afraid,
when people aren't being kind to each
other, and being the one person
who stands up and shares things
in a difficult time,
then  That is an extremely pure person.
That is great karma.
That is incredible karma,
much more powerful.
I think the virus is a very good
time,
a very good opportunity
for all of us to show: Are
we truly Buddhists? Are
we truly practicing the
bodhisattva path?
Can we help others even when things
are so difficult?
Next image.
This one is hard to remember; I have difficulty
recalling it. I'll
give you a second to try to think
about what this image is.
Okay. Pabongka Rinpoche was quoting
some books
with a very, very common ending
from different books.
He quoted a famous one, which says:
(BLO BZANG RGYAL BA'I BSTAN PA CIG)
(BLO BZANG RGYAL BA'I BSTAN PA CIG). It
means:
"May the teachings of the Victorious
Lobsang Drakpa, Je Tsongkhapa,
be spread throughout this world."
And you're thinking,
"We have to go online,
we have to translate this Lam Rim
into many languages."  We must
try to spread the good word
to as many people as possible."
That's the end of the sentence, and we're supposed to
leave
this Lam Rim class or video
and share the Dharma
with people.
And we are supposed to spread the Dharma
throughout the world.
And in this part of the Lam Rim,
Pabongka Rinpoche said, "Look,
the place where you're supposed to spread
the Dharma
is here, inside your own heart."
Don't think that spreading
the Dharma means
trying to translate the videos into more languages
or something like that.
That's a very important spreading
of the Dharma,
but he says, "If you spread it
in your own heart,
then of course it will spread
out of you."
Because the world comes from your heart.
From your heart chakra, actually.
Next picture, number 7.
Try to remember what
this picture was about. I'll
give you a second.
Yes. This is one of my favorite themes,
having a personal relationship
with another person,
like the one these two people have.
In my opinion, and in Tantra, it's one of the
happiest things that can happen to you.
It's one of the most wonderful things
that can happen to you.
Anyone can tell you that the reason
everyone is looking for a partner
is because it makes people happy; it's one
of the greatest blisses.
When everything is going well,
it's one of the  the greatest joys you
can have.
But, you and I know that when it's not right, it's
one of life's greatest miseries.
Why is this relevant to this course here?
If your morals are good,
it's the happiest thing in your life.
And if you break your morals,
it's the same thing that will make you miserable.
It's like having a good woman or man
as your partner;
the same person who makes you totally happy
can also make you totally miserable.
So in this case, Vinaya,
your personal practice of kindness,
good behavior,
is being compared to a partner
who can make the best thing in your life,
or the worst thing in your life—the same person.
Next idim. Number 8, I think.
This was a tricky one. Let's see
if you can remember it.
I'll take a sip of my green drink.
Thank you, Vinaya.
Yes.
This really represents breaking
your commitments.
Pulling up a weed represents breaking
Why...? I mean, destroying this plant
is breaking your commitment.
If you're a gardener, you know you have to pull up
the weeds
before the seeds are ready.
If you wait until  So that the seeds are ready
to fall,
and then you pull up the plant,
you're going to scatter about a thousand seeds.
By the next month or year,
you're going to have thousands of weeds
growing again.
So you have to attack those weeds
in advance.
This relates to a very radical statement
that the Buddha made,
(DGE SLONG DAG SROG DANG
BRAL ZHING SHI BA NI BLA'I)
It is better to die than to break your vows.
Why?
When you break your vows,
you are setting in motion seeds
that will continue to fall for
many lifetimes.
If you die, you ruin one
body-mind set.
If you die, you ruin a very useful temple,
a physical temple and a mind.
You lose one.
But if you break your commitments,
you lose many body-mind sets.
You ruin your body and mind for many lifetimes.
And you kind of set in motion the seeds
that are going to ruin many lifetimes. The
Buddha was saying,
"It is better to die than to break your vows."
And he wasn't being metaphorical.
He was speaking very literally
when he said that.
Better to die than to break your commitments.
There's a joke in the Lam Rim.
We take the  The vow not to renounce
bodhichitta,
even at the cost of our lives.
There is a famous saying
that throughout our lives we
are waiting to be
thrown in jail by
some evil people.
They come with a knife and say to you, "Renounce
your bodhisattva vows or die today."
So we're going to say, "I choose to die."
And they kill us.
I think we're all waiting... ever since
we took that vote, we've
all been waiting for these guys to show up
with knives and threaten us.
But in reality, we're the guys
with knives.
We threaten our bodhisattva vows
every day.
We have to make this decision every
day,
when we carefully decide whether or not to keep
our vows.
It's hard to find those types who throw you
in jail and say,
"I'm going to kill you if you don't renounce
your bodhisattva vows."
The following image
is... See if you can remember it.  I'm
going to give you a minute to try
to remember.
This was a reference...
we have the
"Mixed Nuts" translation team,
and we were translating an ancient
Vinaya text,
monk's vows, nun's vows.  They
were talking about the vow, the tradition
that we shouldn't...
when you become a monk or nun, they
give you your robes, they
give you a small Buddha statue
and they give you a strainer.
And in ancient India, you were supposed to bring
this strainer with you.
When you drink water from a stream, you are supposed to
strain the water first
to make sure you don't kill
any small insects.
We mentioned a famous tradition
in the Vinaya,
that if a couple of monks walk
towards the water,
to a stream to get some water,
then they must choose the friendliest monk
to check the water.
Don't choose the one who doesn't care
about insects.
Try to find someone who loves
insects
and ask them to check the water.  Because they will be
more careful.
What's the point?
We're talking about a type of ecological vows,
where monks and nuns are
not even supposed to...
pick green leaves from a plant,
because they are the homes
of small creatures.  It
means respecting even the
smallest votes,
taking them very seriously
because the results
multiply exponentially.
So it's important to keep your morality
at a very subtle level, at a very fine level.
And don't be picky.
If I were to write the bodhisattva vows,
I would write an additional bodhisattva vow
about not being fussy about your
bodhisattva vows.  There's
nothing more irritating
than a person who...
tells you they're keeping their vows and therefore
have to act like an idiot today.
Keep your vows sweetly.  Keep them happy.  Do
n't exaggerate.
Don't bother people with your votes, because votes are
not meant to bother people.
Keep the votes small, keep them
quiet, keep them personal,
don't advertise them.
There is a saying in Islam: The left hand should not
know what the right hand is doing.
It means, don't announce your votes.
Just keep them quiet.
And keep them at a very fine level.
Next image.
This is the idea that being kind
to other people
is like planting a tree.
Oh, and today I went to the "Peach Tree Cafe"
to check something out, and
Stanley, Allison, and I planted a peach tree there
when we started the "PeachTree Cafe
Morning Show".
And I want to tell you that this week there were
three peaches
and... we already have peaches!
What it means is: take care of the foundation
of your practices, take care of the root,
plant good karma by keeping your vows and
being kind to people.
Then that will grow into a tree.
And that peach tree that we planted,
about five months ago, is
already bearing a lot of fruit.
If you didn't take care of him when he was little, you wouldn't
have anything.
But if you take care of the foundation of your
Buddhist practice,
which is being kind to people,
then the fruits will be thousands
and thousands and thousands.
It will come, and it will grow into a huge...
it will grow into a tree, it will bear
peaches every year and for many years
you will have peaches.
Keep, protect... this girl is
carefully protecting the outbreak.
Protect your morality.
Very good.  Next image.
If I remember correctly, there were four conditions
that could cause you to break
your commitments.
If you took the Bodhisattva commitments
or the Vinaya Pratimoksha commitments,
or even if you took the Diamond Way commitments... tantric commitments.
I think there were four of them.  Pabongka Rinpoche reviewed...
No, maybe more than that, anyway.
There were certain conditions that would help you
break your vows.
If you want to break your vows, there are some
special ways to do it.
Here's the first one, which is:
If you don't know what your votes are, then
that's a good way to break them.
If you want to break them, then
don't study them.
And one of my annoyances—I have many things
that bother me in the Dharma—
is the teachers who give initiations,
great initiations, and don't explain to the people
who are taking the initiation
that they have just taken vows.
There are hundreds of vows you take
when you have an initiation,
and you're going to break them if you don't know them.
It is the teacher's responsibility to
train you on the vows before you
have an initiation.
If they don't offer training, I wouldn't take
any initiation from them.
The best way to break your vows, in the first place,
is not to know them.
Read the recipe before you start cooking.
That's what Veronica tells me every time I
cook.
Next image.
It's a lady saying, "Yes, it's not such a
big deal."
That vow of, I don't know...
not cutting green plants without saying a prayer,
"Come on, that's a little extreme.
It's a little excessive.
That's not a big deal, it's just some insects
that might be using that leaf
as a roof now and then,
so it's not a big deal."
The second big way to break
your vows
is to have this attitude:
"Oh, that's not a big deal, I'm keeping
the bigger ones."
Okay. Next up.
If we have a klesha, meaning
if we have any kind of negativity
circulating in our minds,
that's a great way to break your vows.
Getting upset with someone,
or obsessing over acquiring something, money,
or clinging to our Netflix at night.
That kind of... By the way, it's not wrong to watch Netflix,
but I'm talking about...
hurting someone else because you want to get home
and watch Netflix. That's a problem.
So,
this is called "A Gang Fight,"
and the story is, what?
Go after the big guy on the other side.
Figure out who the leader on the other side is,
and don't talk, don't negotiate, don't...  Scream,
go up to him and hit him on the head.
And then that whole side is going to fall apart.
Identify your worst bad habit,
and go after it first. That's the way
to keep your vows.
The next one.
If you...
By the way, at the age of... my age, I'm not telling you
how old I am,
but this whole young love thing
is so ridiculous from my age's point of view
.
And I can say that from experience because I've been through it
But this thing of:
"Oh, she's the most beautiful woman
in the world."
"He's the most handsome guy in the world."
First of all...
my older brother said something really funny, he
said to me, "Do you like that girl?" I answered, "Yes."
He said, "Do you want to spend your life with her?" I
said, "Yes."
He said, "First go to her mother."  "Look at how
her mother looks."
So I go over and the mother looks terrible. She's overweight, she
looks tired, she looks awful.
And she said to me, "Well, how do you think she looked
at the beginning?"  So think about it.
If you're attached to
a person's appearance,
or something physical, or something not very important
about a person,
that's going to change, and you're going to see them get
sick, you're going to see them
age, you're going to see them get diarrhea
and vomit.
If you're unlucky, you're going to see their insides in surgery
at some point.
So don't fool yourself into thinking it's
worth hurting other people
to get the most beautiful woman or man
you can. It's not worth it. It wo
n't last.
It's great to have a relationship, but have it
for the right reason.
Okay, next.
If you have an anger problem
or get annoyed easily,
then fantasize about giving this person
something they'll love having.
This is called maitri, jampa, love.
Fantasize, try to remember
how nice it is to
give someone something they love,
something they want,
and try to have this attitude.
If you don't feel friendly toward another person,
then have fantasies—which means
meditation—
about giving them something
they really like.
The next one.
It's... I'm
going to give you a moment to  This one. I bet you ca
n't remember what this one is.
Tim's cheating by looking ahead.
What was this one again?
Okay, this one's about pride.
Pride is also going to be a hindrance
to keeping your vows.
And one of the most common kinds of pride
in a monastic setting, which is where
this book was taught,
is: How much do you know about the scriptures?
How many events have you accumulated in your life?
And this is something I really enjoy, the unknown events of the Dharma,
and the more you accumulate, the more you feel
like you're special.
And Pabongka Rinpoche said,
"All the Dharma you have learned in your life,
all the things you have memorized,
all the things you have debated,
all the degrees of Geshe you could have,
compared to what you have left to learn, you
know nothing."
You're like a worm at the bottom of the sea."
And sometimes you come up and see the stars.
Many of those stars have planets around them.
There are people on those planets. There are things
to know about those people.
The things we know that we're
so proud to know
are a very, very, very small fraction
of what you could know.
So don't be proud.
Next.
One of the biggest motivations
for breaking your vows
or your commitments, your morality, which will prevent you from
reaching nirvana,
which will prevent you from reaching the second level
of Lam Rim, personal nirvana,
is understanding emptiness, studying emptiness.
If you realize that the bad things
someone is doing to you
are coming directly from what you did
last week,
then you're not going to make big mistakes.
The more you can study emptiness,
the more you can study cause and effect,
dependent origination,
which means, "That person comes
from my seeds,"
then it's going to be easier to keep
your vows. It's going to be easier.
So study, study, study. I
had a teacher,  He said...
an old Mongolian master,
very old, with tuberculosis.
He used to say:
"He is very good.  You're so proud, you have
a lot of Princeton pride,
"and then the Geshe thing, that's very useful,
very useful.
" So you'll push yourself harder
just to look smart.
"That's fortunate, but later on,
try to give that up.
Just study to be a good person."
It's very funny.  He gave me
Adam's text
on his deathbed.
I remember this.
The following
is technically the fourth cause, is it
?  No, whatever.
One of the reasons for breaking your vows
or losing your commitments
is that it is very difficult in the modern world
to keep your mind on your vows when you are
very busy.
When things are moving
very fast
and there are a thousand things to see on the internet,
and life is moving very fast,
it's difficult to maintain that self-awareness
of: "Am I breaking my vows, am I doing
something to hurt someone?"
So you need to slow down,
return to your vows,
and maintain some kind of sensitivity, some
awareness,
to the fact that you have commitments
not to hurt people.
The busier things get,
the more careful you have to be.
It's easy to have... It
's even easy to get annoyed with your partner
when you're very busy.  They're
trying to tell you something
and you have ten things happening
at work,
and you're like, "Look, I don't have time
to listen to you right now.
My boss gave me ten things to do."
Those are the moments when you need to slow down
and return to your vows,
and don't forget your commitment to be kind
to people,
even when you're very stressed,
very busy.
It's better to break some
business commitments than to get nervous, stressed, and unfriendly to people.
It's better not to pay a bill or miss a business meeting
or not do your best
at your job,
if that means keeping
your mind clear.
Next image.
This is a lady buying something useless
in the store.
See if you can remember this story.
She said, "Oh, this box is very beautiful."  She
went to a department store.
She bought this... What's it like?  What is that place
for the house, where you buy things?
Crate and Barrel.
She went to Crate and Barrel in the United States and
bought this.
She said, "Oh, my husband is going to love this box
."
She has no idea what she's going to use it for,
but she's going to take it home.
Then,
when she gets home, her husband will say, "Are you crazy?
This is just a little box that's useless.
We have enough junk in the house."  "
Give it back, get your money back."
Now, should I go to the gas station
and try to return it?
No, that's not where she got the box.
It's obvious, but we have to mention it.
If you buy a stupid box
because you liked it and think your husband will
like it, which he won't,
and he convinces you to return it,
don't return it to a different place,
return it to the place where you bought it.
What does that mean?
You should pay me.
When it's time to confess,
when you've broken a vow,
then try to go back to the person
who gave you the vow.
Try to confess in front of the person
who gave you the vow. Is
it okay to confess at home alone?
Not for vows you took from other people.
Generally,
if you didn't take a vow from someone else,
then maybe it's okay to do it at home,
confess in front of a Buddha statue or something,
in extreme cases it's okay.
But generally,
if you can go back to the person
who gave you your vows
and confess to them  Openly, without shame.
We're shameless all day long.
So, to be shameless about your vows,
just say, "What the hell."
Go straight to your teacher and say,
"I tore up this stupid vow."
And your teacher is like, "Wow!"  "You're a
very bad person!" And you say, "Yes, I am." Get over
it. And then you feel so clean,
you feel so good. You
can be shy about a lot of things
in your life, but don't be shy about your vows.
If you break a vow, tell someone,
and that's how you get rid of it.
You get rid of the problem.
If you keep it and hide it, if you spend more time hiding it
than confessing it, or holding onto it,
then it's just foolish,
and you won't feel good, you won't feel clean.
Just be upfront with your teachers:
"I have this problem."  "I have this bad habit."
The karma is destroyed, the seed is destroyed.
And you know, your teacher is going to say, "I've heard
that before, you've told me that before."
But be persistent and keep telling them.
Next picture.
This one's about... wait, remember?
Again, it's about honoring
the little details of vows.
And they were talking...
It's actually a vow for monks to
brush their teeth,
with a stick, which was called (SO SHING).
It was a stick that you were to use to clean your
teeth,
and you just cut it from a tree
and use it. It's a toothbrush.
And it's said that the monks should have their
toothbrushes and you should brush your teeth. It
might seem like a small thing:
"Wait, I'm trying to keep my
tantric vow to go to Amitabha's paradise
and protect all living beings."
And Buddha says, "Yes, but in the meantime, could you please
brush your teeth every day?"
And you say, "But that's not a big vow."
"Yes,  But it's the little things
that make up Buddha's paradise.
It's the little things that bodhisattvas do,
the things that are kind to others.
Of course, everyone in the world is
going to, I don't know...
stop a nuclear war or something, if they can,
I mean, it's obvious.
But are you a good enough person
that you don't even want people to
smell your breath if it could hurt them?
If you're very sensitive
to the little things that could
hurt people,
then we can say that you're upholding
your morals.
And then it's the little details that give
the finishing touches
to your Buddha's paradise, which you see
in the next picture.
This is this person decorating a Christmas tree. I do
n't know if you've ever put up a
Christmas tree,
but those of us who grew up
in the Christian tradition had Christmas
trees put up by our parents
.
And there's something great about putting on the last ornament.
Everyone is looking at the tree and they say,
"Is it done yet?" And they say, "Yes, it's done."
Then they say, "Wait, there's one more
we should put on there."
This Christmas ornament
is the  Brushing your teeth.
It's the little finishing touches you
put into your Buddhahood.
It's the small things that make
Buddhas. It's
not the grand things, it's not
the big things.
It's paying attention to the small details
of making people happy that creates
a Buddha.
Very good.
Next one.
See if you remember this one. I'll give you a hint:
Yamantaka, Yamantaka.
This is a famous story from the Lam Rim.
Monks and nuns are supposed to attend
sojong twice a month and confess
the mistakes they've made to each other
openly.
The master said,
"They hit the gunty.  They struck the gunty,
which is a special piece of wood,
it looks like a 2x4 beam,
and you strike it with another stick and it goes:
thunk, thunk, thunk.
And that's a bell. That was an old bell,
before metal was common.
They'll strike the board and when you hear that,
you have to go to sojong. They
still do it.
I made a gunty with my Master. He wanted one.
We made it with the correct...
there are many rules about it.
And when you hear the gunty, you're
supposed to hold it here,
hold the gunty here and stick it like this.
Then all the monks
and nuns are supposed to come to confession.
So, this master said,
"Hey, they struck the gunty."  "Let's go."
The student said, "No, I'm not going to
confession today."
The master said, "What?!"
Because that is one of
a monk's main commitments, to go to sojong.
The master said, "What are you talking about?"
He said, "I don't have to go today."
The master said, "What do you mean you do
n't have to go today?"
And he said, "You forgot that you gave me a
Yamantaka initiation yesterday."
I am Yamantaka, I am a Buddha.  "I don't need to
go to sojong anymore."
The master grabs him by the ear and says,
"What the hell are you, Yamantaka?"
Yamantaka is going to go sojong with me right now
."
"Ahhhh."
What it means is: "Don't tell me these things
about you being a great tantrika,
"and you're beyond morality
and now you have a higher vision."
It's a completely wrong idea.
If you have a secret initiation,
then you should go to sojong
every morning or something.
You should go more than other people.
Because that's what it gives you... that's what
empowers your tantric practice:
being kind to other people
and confessing when you make a mistake.
Following.
This is a sad image.  We
always think of morality
as the roots of our practice,
the foundation of our practice.
But Pabongka Rinpoche kind of turned it around
.
This is a perfect image.
He said, "Imagine an apple tree
that someone cut in half."  He
actually used the palm tree.
Someone sliced ​​it up and cut off the
top of the tree.
So you won't have any leaves,
not even a single leaf will come out,
therefore you won't get any flowers,
and therefore you won't get the fruit
that always comes from the flowers.  You're
not going to achieve anything.
A person who is not kind to other people
day after day, hour after hour,
cuts off any opportunity
to reap those beautiful fruits
of practice.
Very good.  The next one.
This was an idea from something my Master
asked me... I'm
sorry, I asked my Master and I don't know
if you remember, but I asked him:
The first of the Five Paths,
the path of accumulation, you
reach it when you have
a personal tragedy,
but, if you are on the bodhisattva track you
reach it when you obtain bodhichitta.
I said, "I don't understand what is tragic
about bodhichitta."
And he said to me, "'No, no, no. It's still a matter
of tragedy.
It's just the tragedy of every living being;
every being in this universe
has the same tragedy.'
So, in truth, that communal tragedy
is the beginning of the Five Paths.
Thinking about that tragedy
is the beginning of the Five Paths for
a bodhisattva. So it really is the same thing.
The puppy is having difficulties, but now all
the puppies in the basket are having difficulties.
We're all in this together.
And that's the beginning of bodhichitta.
This next image is a man shaking
hands with someone in his office.
I imagine the woman is introducing them: '
This is Joe; he works in the advertising department.'  "
This is Sam, he works in the
IT department." They
shake hands.
Remember what this is?
It was a really, really nice exercise where we were supposed to
close our eyes
and think about the person who annoys us the most.
And see if we could get angry.
The problem with this kind of exercise
is that after about ten minutes
you forget it's an exercise,
and you actually get angry.
"Let me see if I can get angry."
"How are you going to do that?"
"I'm going to think about this guy who made me angry
this week." "Okay, go ahead."
Then, slowly, the person starts to tremble.
And you say, "What's going on?"
"I got angry."  The experiment worked."
If it's your Lama, they'll say,
"Notice how you feel when you start
thinking about this person."
How does it feel? What comes to your heart? I do
n't know about you, but I feel a little unease
in my heart;
I start to feel a kind of discomfort
here or there.
When I think about a person who has been
bothering me or a problem that's bothering me,
I can deliberately create tension
within myself.
He says, "Let's do an exercise.  Try to create
some tension in your heart,
then observe that tension and become familiar with it.
As if you were shaking someone's hand.
Learn what it feels like
when a mental affliction,
a negative emotion,
begins to rise in your heart,
and keep practicing.
As soon as you feel better and forget
about this person, think about them again.
See if you can get angry again. See if you can
start to get angry again.
And try to familiarize yourself with what it feels like,
shake their hand: "Hello."  "He's Geshe Michael."
"Hello, what's your name?"
"I'm starting to get angry with this person."
"Ah."  Pleased to meet you.  Now
I know what you look like.
Now I can keep an eye on things.  "
I can avoid you in the future."
Okay. Next up.
It's called: Visiting the Center of the Sun.
The theme of this Lam Rim, which was:
Love in the Time of the Virus.
The virus is a big thing, it's spread all over
the world.
I've lived a long life and thought I'd
seen it all.
I entered my 60s and thought, "Well, now nothing
new is going to happen."
"I'm pretty ready for anything
that might happen. I've
seen it all, and nothing can bother me too much."
Then this virus appears and threatens
everyone in the world.
And I'm like, "Wow! That's huge,
that covers the whole planet."  I do
n't know if it happened to you, but it happened to me.  It is
probably...
negative action number nine,
which is ill will.
Being happy when someone else has
a problem.
When I heard that annoying, famous people were getting sick,
I was like, [laughs] I did
n't want them to die or anything,
but I was like, "See? I told you it was bad
to be bad."
And then I realized I was
thinking that way myself.  It
feels like something big.
It feels like...
this problem has spread across the entire
planet.
And it feels like something that's difficult
for me to deal with.
But, we just entered
after ten years of studying
the Lam Rim, we just
entered the path for the
most capable people.  We
are going to open that study
with the idea of ​​bodhichitta.
What is bodhichitta?  It is
not: enlightened mind.  Forget
about that incredibly bad translation.
It is my wish that I may become a Buddha
to help countless living beings.
And there is a direct experience of this,
in the same way that there is a
direct experience of emptiness.
There are parallel experiences that we
must reach in this life.
And again, you should be
meditating.
We described an extraordinary...
what do you call it?  Discovery?
Threshold experience,
where you enter a deep state
of meditation, and,
because time and space come
from seeds,
if you can alter these seeds,
then you can compact time
and space.
In a meditation that lasts no more
than half an hour,
you could actually visit every person
in the universe,
including animals and bugs
and birds and fish,
and you could communicate with each one
individually,
within the half hour,
and with each one you can make
a commitment.
I mean, you know them, you see that each one
is suffering,
each one is having a difficult life
and is worried about the future.
You could go to each one separately
and say,
"I've got you covered, take it easy."
I used to work... when I was
at university I
got a scholarship, but they told me I had to work a few hours a week.
And it turned out to be 30 hours a week.  I was supposed to
drive a truck,
actually, first they sent me to a cafeteria
and told me I had to mop the floor.
I quit within ten hours.  I quit on
the first day.
Then they told me, "You can drive a truck."
I said, "That's fun. I'm going to drive a truck.
I drove a truck for five years.
We had a guy,
a permanent employee of the university,
named Big John,
his name was Big John. He was Polish, over six feet
tall, a huge guy.
Everyone was scared of him when they saw him, they were
scared of him,
but he was extremely sweet.
He brought donuts to work and he was
from Trenton, New Jersey.
Trenton.
He did the best things for us and covered for us.
One day we broke the truck in half.
We hit a tree with the truck
and broke it in half.
And he covered for us: 'Oh, these bolts weren't tight enough.'"
"I don't know what happened. The truck fell apart.
Do
n't blame these kids."
All they did was drive him around."
Then he winked at us and said, "I've got you
covered."  "I've got you covered."
I always think of him when I think
of bodhichitta.
You're going to meet every living being
in the universe directly,
and you're going to say, "Big John's got you covered."  I've got you
covered.  Don't worry.  Do
n't worry.  "I've got you covered."
That's bodhichitta. And you must have that experience,
you should work for that experience.
You have to meditate, you have to study
bodhichitta,
you have to study the Lam Rim
on bodhichitta.
You have to take all those steps, like...
exchanging yourself for others.
And one day you will have that experience and you will meet every
living being,
and you will say to them, "I've got you covered."  Don't worry, I've
got you covered.
Big Mike is looking after you,"
or Big Tim, or Big Seiji.
"Don't worry."  Do
n't stress.  "I'm on it."
That's exactly what it feels like.
It's a personal commitment.
Why are we talking about that? Ah.
You're going to do that in countless worlds.
When you do it, the day you do it, you'll do it
in countless worlds.
An action that directly engages
with every living creature in countless worlds
has no problem taking care of a single virus
in a single world.
That's nothing.
A virus that endangers
7 or 8 billion people is nothing
compared to bodhichitta.
It's like... we said, if you spill ketchup
on your shirt
and deliver that shirt into the center of the sun,
which is 25 million degrees Fahrenheit,
the ketchup stain
will probably disappear. You
probably don't have to worry
about the ketchup stain.
Work on your bodhichitta and you'll destroy
the virus, by the way, by accident. It's
not a big deal.
Next image.
"Don't mess with other paths."
Learn bodhichitta. Learn to have
this experience.
Don't waste your time.
Don't focus on other things.
Focus.  in bodhichitta,
and then you won't have to do things
twice.
We're talking about doing things twice.
This lady is in a hurry;
she says, "I don't have time for these
bodhichitta things."  "
I'm going to go straight to tantra."
Well, you're still going to have to go back and pick up
that thing you forgot, which is bodhichitta.
Work on your bodhichitta first. You do
n't have to go back home and pick up
bodhichitta and come back.
This was a radical example,
the next picture.
This one is hard to remember. I'll give you a second
to think about it. I do
n't know if you remember this...
This is a bit complicated. A
group of 60 boys and girls were about
to reach nirvana
simply by seeing emptiness directly
and without bodhichitta, a
lower nirvana.
Then Manjushri appears and teaches them
about bodhichitta.
Maybe he taught about the experience we just
talked about. They
were all annoyed with Manjushri.
They were like, "Don't waste our time."
"We are close to nirvana. We can feel it.
We can taste it. We
all already perceive emptiness, don't waste
our time."  "
Don't talk to us about this."
And because they had disrespected
a teaching about bodhichitta,
they went to hell. They did
n't reach
nirvana. They fell into the realms
of hell.
But they burned it out
and became human again,
after many millions of years. Deep down, there
was this teaching that Manjushri
had given them about bodhichitta, and they remembered it.
And they became bodhisattvas and became
Buddhas.
That would take less time
than entering a lower nirvana without studying
bodhichitta. It
would be faster to go to hell and come back
and start over with bodhichitta than if you did
n't use bodhichitta
and went to a lower nirvana.
This is a picture of someone sending someone
down the wrong road, on purpose.
This lady is asking,
"Where is that super highway that goes to the store I
want to visit?"
The guy knows the road
is blocked,
so he tells her, "Listen, don't go down that road,
the road is blocked."  "Go the other way."
And she insists: "No.  "Tell me where
the road I want is."
Then he lies to her and says,
"Ah, go that way." It's actually the long way
he wanted her to take anyway.
This is a story about what
skillful means mean.
Next picture.
This is warming up before running a race.
We usually use this picture about what? Do
you remember?
It's breath meditation. We
usually say, "Look,
breath meditation is just a warm-up.
Don't think of it as the race."
In the Olympics, there's no
stretching contest before the race. There's
no such thing; you don't get a gold medal
for stretching.
But in this case, we're not talking
about breath meditation;
we're talking about how it's good to do
the Three Main Paths in order:
Be sad about this world;
strive to have that experience
of bodhichitta directly;
and see emptiness so you can help
everyone.
Warm up with the first feelings
of sadness about this life.
Now, next picture. We're
almost done. I think we're very close.  Are
we close? Not so close, well! Do
you remember who these guys are?
They're a really bad band.
I guess you find them in malls
or something, singing bad songs.
It's called: the opening act. So,
the steps on the path for the less
capable:
trying to reach a higher rebirth;
the steps on the path
for the average capable:
trying not to return to this world at
all;
the steps on the path for the most capable:
these two levels are just the
opening act,
and this is the main thing, reaching bodhichitta.
What's above bodhichitta?
The six perfections.
Check it out:
the steps on the path to keep yourself out
of the lower realms; the
steps on the path to reach nirvana;
and then we have bodhichitta,
this experience of meeting every living being
and making the commitment: "I'm going to take care of you."  "
I'm going to take care of you."
And up here are the six...
this is six in Chinese. Up here
are the six perfections.
Now,
which of these is the big one? Which is the real band? Which is the opening act?
These guys, obviously, the lower nirvana,
aren't the big deal.
But what's interesting is,
Pabongka Rinpoche says, "That experience
with every living being
" is the main act. That's what I want you to
focus on. "
I want you to try to have that experience."
If you have that experience, we can talk
about the Six Perfections."
Including number six, which is perceiving
emptiness.
"Let's talk about that later."
Come on, I want you guys to focus
on having this experience.
By the way, a good way to have that experience
is to imagine that experience
and try to hear the description
of it,
and pretend you can do it
and keep pretending.
Keep doing it.
It feels like a slot machine.
I like to say, "It feels like a
slot machine."
When you pull the lever
on a slot machine,
these images come up,
cherries, and other things—
not that I've ever played
a slot machine.
Well, once, with my dad.
You pull the lever and then these markers
come up like this. Just imagine that.
Your mother's face appears,
and you say, "Mom, you look worried."
She's like, "Yeah, I'm worried about life."
And you say, "Don't worry, Big John
has you covered."
Just calm down.  I have it.  "I'm working on it."
Then your dad's picture appears—
not just the image, but the person
appears. That's how it
feels in meditation. So try to
imagine it, try to practice it,
and it will activate the real. It will activate the real.
Bring people in, one by one,
see how they feel,
make a commitment: "Don't worry."  I've
got you covered.  "I'm on it."
Then he goes on, brings another person.
And he practices like that. You can do it with five
or six people.
It will be faster, because time will change.
Very well,
and Pabongka Rinpoche is saying
that's the main show,
those are the Rolling Stones.
The rest are just new bands
that aren't very good.
Who's at the end? Do they have a final act?
Usually not.
Anyway, what follows is just leaving
the stadium or something. Don't worry.
Now we cross over to the ten great things
about having bodhichitta. We'll
only have time to look at the first one
in this Lam Rim.
The first fantastic thing about getting
bodhichitta is:
if you were a "nerdy" kid
playing tennis in school,
and your dream was to be on the team,
then,
next picture.
No...
Yes! There's Geshe Michael in the center,
up top, not the weird kids down below.
You can be on the team, and it's great to be
on the bodhisattva team.
Work to be on that team.
It's so great to be on that team
because that team spreads  throughout the entire
universe.
It's all the great people in the entire universe.
So it's nice to be part of that team.
It's sweet.
That was the first benefit of bodhichitta.
Now, next picture.
This is a guy visiting an
art museum.
He talked about the two levels of tantra. The
first level is meeting angels; the
second level is studying from them how to be
an angel and becoming an angel.
At the first level, we're supposed to
actually meet
real angels, in person. It's
not like standing in an art museum and seeing
a statue or a person's thangka; it's
meeting the person directly,
and that's totally something else entirely.
If you try to practice tantra
without that bodhichitta experience,
then it will be like looking at pictures of Buddhas
instead of meeting Buddhas. They
don't like talking to people
who don't have bodhichitta. They
feel more comfortable
around people who have had this experience. So try to have this experience.
And then tantra will work for you.
And if you don't have this experience,
tantra is going to be difficult.
It's going to be like looking at pictures of Buddhas instead of meeting them.
of hanging out with Buddhas.
Okay, next one.
If you try to practice tantra without bodhichitta,
you could have bad results.
And we're talking about the first nuclear test
in modern times.
Scientists admitted that this explosion
could set the whole world on fire. They
were just trying to do something cool,
but they were risking
a huge disaster.
That's tantra without bodhichitta.
That's like accidentally setting the whole sky on fire
. You're going to mess it up.
Next one.
Even small, neutral karmas
become powerful for a person
with bodhichitta.
A person with bodhichitta can feed
a bird,
say a prayer about it,
and that affects millions of people.
They have this power.
Next picture.
Even small bad actions, like stealing
a French fry and giving it to a bird,
could be powerful if done by
a bodhisattva.
But it's a dangerous practice.
We're not at that level. We're not at that level.
We're not at that level.
"Did you hear that?"
"No."
We have a picture of a fugu fish.
People in Japan,  Real men
eat this fish. It
has very, very poisonous parts that can kill you
instantly; 50 people die every year in Japan.
But people still go to restaurants.
To be able to serve this fish in a restaurant,
you need three years of special training,
or you could kill someone.
That's the same as stealing a French fry
to give to a bird
because you want to help the bird.
We're not at that level. Don't try to eat
fugu fish if you're not trained.
Then we have a very nice picture of Nick
and Erin with their big boss,
who is Amalie. Hello, Amalie.
Amalie represents the Buddha,
and Nick represents the father,
who is bodhichitta, and Erin represents
wisdom,
which is the direct perception
of emptiness.
And, in a way,
somehow—I don't know what the belief is in Asia—
but in a way, the father is irreplaceable.
Something special about the father, I do
n't know what it is. But anyway…
You can see emptiness on different levels,
on all three tracks.
But bodhichitta, you have to be
a person  Special. You
can only see it on the highest track. It
defines you as a person
on the highest track.
And you need both to have your baby,
which is Buddhahood.
Next picture.
We said (Tibetan).
Which Tim correctly identified today.
What is your main practice? What is the thing
that is number one in your life right now?
Until the next Lam Rim, the Lam Rim
of the Medicine Buddha, in October?
Look, I want you to treat this
as your main practice:
Trying to have that experience of meeting
countless beings. Try to have that experience. I do
n't care if you sit there hour after hour
and nothing happens,
just try, just pretend,
just run it through in your mind until
the next Lam Rim.
Let's make a deal. Make it
your main practice.
Next picture.
If that practice weren't so important, then one
of the greatest Buddhists of all time,
Lord Atisha, wouldn't have sailed for
13 months risking his life
to get the teachings
on bodhichitta that you just received
in this video.
And no  You didn't have to go anywhere.
If Atisha thought it was worth
risking his life for 13 months
on a small boat in the Pacific
and Indian Oceans,
then maybe it's important,
maybe it was worth it.
Next picture.
I think the dumbest thing you can do
in your entire life
is go to Paris and not buy a croissant.
Okay? I'm just saying, there are
probably other dumb things
you can do in your life,
but for me, the ultimate dumbness
is going to Paris and not going to a boulangerie,
or at least buying a crepe
on the street
with... what's that chocolatey stuff?
Nutella, yes.
Not eating a Nutella crepe.
Going to Paris and not eating a Nutella crepe,
then that shows you're crazy.
If you're studying Lam Rim,
if you've gotten this far in Lam Rim, and Geshehla
has been teaching it for ten years,
and you'll finally get to the croissant,
which is the bodhichitta experience, don't
go crazy and leave Paris without one.  Eat it.
Don't leave Lam Rim without having this experience. You'd
be a fool.
We're done! With the croissant.
I think you want to make a presentation?
No? I was assuming there might be
a croissant in that bag.
Right. Tim Lowenhaupt is going to make
a formal presentation
to Geshehla, my payment.
Oh, is it a... bread...?
What do you call it?
Seiji.
What's it called?
Chocolate bread, chocolate bread.
Here, you have to divide it into three parts.
And give me all three... I mean, no, just one.
Very well. I have the chocolate bread.
This is what you give to your teacher
when he teaches you about bodhichitta.
So let's make a deal.
For the next two months,
work on that experience. Do the
dedication chapter in your meditation, from Shantideva.
Try to work on having that experience.
The worst that can happen is that you'll at least
plant seeds in your mind
to have the experience.
Just pretend.
Just sit and fantasize about it.
Fantasize  It's a good meditation.
Imagine that you have this experience
of meeting
each living being, one by one,
and you make a personal commitment
to each one
to care for them in the best possible way.
Very good.
See you at the next Lam Rim
for the Medicine Buddha. Yes!